בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף ס"א, daf samach-aleph,
61. I'd like to dedicate our learning in the memory of my
זיידע zayde עליו השלום alav hashalom מרדכי אליעזר בן משה Mordechai Eliezer
ben Moshe who was perished in the
Holocaust, so his נשמה neshama should have an עליה. aliyah.
We start on the very bottom of סמ"ך עמוד ב'. samach amud-bet.
It is his יארצייט yahrtzeit if I didn't mention that. It is
his
יארצייט. yahrtzeit. Last line of סמ"ך עמוד ב', samach amud-bet, לא ביחיד
בזמן דאין ברגלו מכה. lo beyachid b'zman d'ein b'raglo maka. And we're
going to get into some very interesting discussions today around issues of
תפילין tefillin and קמיע, kameia, those interesting cases in the משנה. mishnah.
So, be prepared. So, the last line is that an individual cannot
wear a—you can't wear a single shoe as if there's if you
don't have a wound on your leg. And רש"י rashi gives two
reasons. One is that people will think you're carrying the other shoe,
or that people will make fun of you and then you'll take
off the one shoe and you'll carry it. Okay, so the גמרא
gemara says היש ברגלו מכה. hayesh b'raglo maka. Top of ס"א עמוד
א', samach-aleph amud-aleph, היש ברגלו מכה. hayesh b'raglo maka. If you have
a wound on your leg, נפיק, nafik, you can go out with
a single shoe. בהינייהו נפיק? b'hainayhu nafik? So, which one is wearing
the shoe? The leg with the wound or the leg without the
wound? So, אמר רב הונא, amar Rav Huna, so says רב הונא,
Rav Huna, באותה שיש בה מכה. b'osah sheyesh bah maka. The one
wearing the wound, I mean the one with the wound. אלמא קסבר
סנדל לשום צער עביד. alma kasavar sandal l'shum tzaar avid. He assumes
that the סנדל sandal is being done for—sounds like is generally made
for to prevent pain, to prevent you from walking on, you know,
a painful road. And therefore, you're specifically wanting to do it for
the one with the wound so it doesn't hurt you even more,
so you're particularly working to protect that from any undue pain. And
therefore, it's a normal thing to do and people understand why you're
doing it. So you're not going to make fun of you or
if they make fun of you, you don't care because you're trying
to avoid pain. And you're not going to come to take it
off and carry or people won't suspect you of carrying the other
one. They understand why it's on the one with the wound. You're
trying to particularly protect it from pain and for whatever reason you
don't need to worry about that as much with the other foot.
That's his opinion. חייא בר רב Chiya bar Rav says, חייא בר
רב Chiya bar Rav says, באותה שאין בה מכה. b'osah she-ein bah
maka. No, you can wear those סנדל sandal on the one without—without
the wound.
אלמא קסבר לשום תענוג עביד. alma kasavar l'shum taanug avid. Why do
you wear a shoe? Not to prevent you from pain, but because
it's, you know, it's more comfortable.
So okay, so you also want the one with the wound to
be more comfortable. But no, you know, sometimes if it's got—if you've
got a wound, then it's actually painful to put on a shoe.
You want your leg free. So you understand why you only want
it on the one with it. You're not trying to prevent additional
pain, which then you would do it for the other one, you're
just trying to do it as a sort of as a, you
know, as a pleasure, as a comfort, and therefore the other issues
would outweigh it on the one with the wound. And again, people
would understand why it's only on one leg and you won't come
to carry it or they won't suspect you of doing something wrong.
וזו שיש בה מכה, v'zo sheyesh bah maka, the one with the
wound, מכתה מוכחת עליה. makasoh mocheches aleha. The wound makes it obvious
why you're not putting it on that one, because it's not about
pain, it's about pleasure, and that's not relevant in this case
with the מכה. maka. Of course, this is a very funny discussion.
I mean, you know, different realities, different people, different types of sandals,
different types of wounds. Like, as if there's one explanation about why
people wear shoes and one reality of מכות makas and why you
would or wouldn't be wearing it. So it's a very sort of
strange what this whole debate is really about.
But they're saying it's
הלכה halacha because—I understand they're saying it's הלכה halacha and I'm saying
I don't really understand it. ואף ר' יוחנן סבר לה להא דרב
הונא. v'af Rabbi Yochanan savar lah l'hada d'Rav Huna. ר' יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan agrees to the position of רב הונא Rav Huna that if
you're only wearing one shoe you would tend to wear it and
you had a מכה, maka, you'd tend to wear it on the
one with the מכה, maka, the leg with the wound. דאמר ליה
ר' יוחנן לרב שמן בר אבא d'amar lei Rabbi Yochanan l'Rav Shemen
bar Abba because ר' יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to רב שמן בר
אבא, Rav Shemen bar Abba, הב לי מסאני. hav li msanai. Give
me my shoes. He was getting dressed, please—maybe he was coming out
of the bathhouse, who knows what he was doing. He says, please
give me my shoes. יהב ליה דימין yahav lei d'yamin and he
gave him the right one first. אמר ליה, amlei, so he said
to him, עשית מכה. asisa maka. You turned my—you turned my leg
into a wounded leg. Why? Because we're about to see that the
גמרא gemara is going to speak about this idea that when you
put on your shoes, you're supposed to put them on in a
particular order. First your left shoe and then your right shoe. So
ר' יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan feels that you can't reverse the order. So
if you're giving me my right shoe first, then I'm going to
and you want me to put it on, I'm only going to
wear a—a shoe on my right leg. Because if I put on
the right shoe first, I can't reverse the order. I have to
go left and right. If I did right, I'm—that's it. So if
you want me to wear a shoe only on my right leg,
you're turning it—you're making a wound in my right leg. People will
think that, you know, why do people wear a shoe on one
leg? 'Cause that's the leg that has a wound on it. So
that's what it does. It's as if you made a wound in
my right leg
and—the right of the person facing?
Well, okay. Anyway, so clearly you see that he feels that if
people are wearing one foot, one shoe and they have a מכה,
maka, they put it on the one with the מכה maka 'cause
he says you turned it into a wounded leg. So the גמרא
gemara says, ודילמא כחייא בר רב סבירא ליה. v'dilma k'Chiya bar Rav
svira lei. How do you know? Maybe he's like חייא בר רב
Chiya bar Rav that people who wear one shoe with a wounded
leg wear it. on the good leg, והכי קאמר, ve'hachi ka'amar, and
this is what he meant, עשיתה דשמאל מכה, asiteih d'semol makkah, you
gave me my right a right shoe, you made it like my
left leg has a wound. He didn't say which leg is it
like a wound, but you said you're going to make me wear
just one shoe because I can't do the reverse order, right and
then left, and then it's like I have a wound. Which leg
has a wound? Who knows? That depends on the debate. If you're
wearing only one shoe, would you wear it on the leg with
the wound or the leg without the wound? Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara doesn't really resolve that, as I said, it's a pretty strange
debate because it's as if there's like one reality of why shoes
are worn with people with wounds. But anyway, now the גמרא Gemara
actually turns to this interesting question of that
about the order of which one normally puts on shoes. So let's
take a look. ואזא רבי יוחנן לטעמיה, ve'aza Rabbi Yochanan l'taimei, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רבי יוחנן כתפילין
כך מנעלים, d'amar Rabbi Yochanan k'tefillin kach min'alim,
like תפילין tefillin so are shoes. So מה תפילין בשמאל, ma tefillin
b'semol, the same way by תפילין tefillin you put תפילין tefillin on
your left hand, אף מנעלים בשמאל, af min'alim b'semol,
even shoes you first put your shoe on your left foot before
your right foot.
So that's discussed in the הלכה halacha whether a lefty would do
it the other way around because a lefty puts תפילין tefillin on
his right arm. So the
גמרא Gemara says... מתיבי, meisivei, I'll ask you on this: כשהוא נועל
נועל של ימין ואחר כך של שמאל. keshe'hu no'el no'el shel yamin
ve'achar kach shel semol. We have a ברייתא baraita that says that
when you tie your shoes, first you tie your left, first you
tie your right and then your left. So how does that fit
with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that says first the left and then
the right?
So אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, השא דתניא הכי ואמר רבי
יוחנן הכי, hasha d'tanya hachi ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi, so we got
one ברייתא baraita that says you put it on your right foot
first when you're putting on your shoes, and the other ברייתא baraita
that says you put it on your left, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says you put it on your left foot first. So דעבי
הכי עבי ודעבי הכי עבי. d'avi hachi avid u'd'avi hachi avid. You
can do whatever you want. You can go like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, you can go like the
ברייתא. baraita. גזונטהייט, gazunteheit, so you're free to choose. The way תוספות
Tosafot says it is you know maybe you're influenced, maybe you're attracted
to this idea of making it like תפילין, tefillin, then you'll adopt
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's approach. Maybe you want to go by the
normal fact that הלכה halacha favors the right. So then you'll put
it on the right one first. Okay, so you have your choice.
It's actually interesting because we have in the ישיבה yeshiva we have
a thing where third and fourth-year students we give them שאלות she'eilot
that were asked to our rabbis in the field and then they
research them and present answers. So one שאלה she'eila was a woman
said that her mother was moving into a new apartment and the
bed, the feet were facing the door, and she was very upset
about this because like you know because she felt like it's totally
inappropriate. They didn't even know why, couldn't find any halachic discussion. But
when he asked people, a lot of people said oh I would
never have my bed that way, that's how you take out a
dead body. So then he said, but he said he looked at
it, he said if you look at the גמרא Gemara it says
that you're supposed to have your bed north-south, but if you look
at the זוהר Zohar it says you're supposed to have your bed
east-west. So he said I would tell her whichever one she's doing
she's either going according to the גמרא Gemara or according to the
זוהר Zohar so she shouldn't worry about it. So anyway, which I
thought was a pretty creative answer. So anyway here's what the גמרא
Gemara says, whichever shoe you want to put on first you have
something to rely on. But one minute, the גמרא Gemara isn't done.
So it says like this: אמר
ליה אביי, amlei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, דילמא רבי יוחנן הא
מתניתין לא הוה שמיע ליה. dilma Rabbi Yochanan ha matnitin lo hava
shmi'a lei. One minute, you can't say both are equal options. Maybe
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan wasn't informed of this ברייתא. baraita. ואי הוה
שמיע ליה הוה הדר ביה, ve'i hava shmi'a lei hava hadar bei,
and maybe had he known the ברייתא baraita he would have reversed
himself. So maybe we should favor, say rule like the ברייתא baraita
that says that it has to be the right foot first, the
right shoe first. ואי נמי שמיע
ליה, ve'i nami shmi'a lei, and maybe the opposite, maybe he knew
about this ברייתא baraita because דרב אין הלכה כמתניתין, d'rav ein halacha
k'matnitin, he felt we don't rule like it. So therefore we should
reject it, meaning you can't say they're both legitimate.
Maybe one is right and one is wrong and we haven't yet
figured that out. So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak, so רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak says,
ירא שמים יוצא ידי שניהם, yere shamayim yotze yedei shteihem, a person
who fears heaven will satisfy both of these teachings. ומני הוא, u'mani
hu, who is this?
מר בריה דרבנא, Mar breih d'Ravna, and היכי עביד, hechi avid, what
would he do? סיים דימינא ולא קטר, siyam d'yamina velo katar, first
he'd put on his right shoe and he wouldn't tie it. וסיים
דשמאלא וקטר, vesiyam d'semola vekatar, then he'd put on his left shoe
and קטר, katar, and then he'd tie the knot on the shoe,
right, he'd put it on his foot but he wouldn't tie the
shoe. Then he'd put the left one on and tie it. והדר
קטר דימינא, ve'hadar katar d'yamina, and then the right one. And as
is pointed out, this is because the preference, why
did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan prefer the left? Normally we're always preferring
the right in הלכה, halacha, but because by תפילין, tefillin, but by
תפילין tefillin what you do on the left is you bind the
left. So therefore the tying of the left shoe corresponds to the
binding of the תפילין. tefillin. So you put on the right first
because of the general favoring of the right, then you put on
the left and then you bind the left like you bind the
תפילין, tefillin, so that's the one you bind first and then you
bind the right. Okay, what if you do loafers? Then you do
right and left. Okay, and that actually is brought down in שלחן
ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. You first do right and then left, and if
it's something you tie, you tie the left first and then you
tie the right first. So, one minute, I will talk about that.
אמר רב אסי, amar Rav Assi, so said רב אסי, Rav Assi,
חזינא לרב כהנא דלא קפיד, chazina l'Rav Kahana d'lo kapid, I saw
רב כהנא Rav Kahana who didn't care. כהנא, Kahana, he didn't care
which one he did first. Okay, so not everybody treats this so
seriously. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught, this is in מסכת
דרך ארץ, Masechet Derech Eretz, which is
ways in which you act in your normal day-to-day behaviors which you
normally wouldn't expect are הלכה, Halacha, but it gives proper ways of
acting. And it
says כשנועל נועל של ימין ואחר כך נועל של שמאל, keshenoel noel
shel yemin ve'achar kach noel shel smol, when you put them on
first you do the right and then the left. Again, this is
the ברייתא Baraita presumably quoted before against רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, but
we found a way to say that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is
also right when it comes to tying it.
כשחולץ, keshecholetz, and when you take them off you do the reverse:
חולץ של שמאל ואחר כך של ימין, choletz shel smol ve'achar shel
yemin, the left one first and then the right one because the
right one is the one that should have the shoe on if
there's only one foot that has the shoe on it should be
the right one.
That I don't know.
כשרוחץ—I kesherocheitz don't think we say that. כשרוחץ רוחץ של ימין ואחר
כך רוחץ של שמאל. kesherocheitz rocheitz shel yemin ve'achar rocheitz shel smol.
Now it's not only about putting on your shoes. When you're
bathing, רוחץ של ימין ואחר כך רוחץ של שמאל, rocheitz shel yemin
ve'achar rocheitz shel smol, first you bathe your right arm or your
right hand and then your left, maybe the right side of your
body and then the left. והרוצה לסוך כל גופו, veharotzeh lasuch kol
gufo, and I'm sorry, כשסך סך של ימין ואחר כך של שמאל.
keshesach sach shel yemin ve'achar shel smol. When you're putting oil, first
you do the right and then the left. והרוצה לסוך כל גופו,
veharotzeh lasuch kol gufo, if you want to put oil on your
whole body. Interesting it didn't say when you want to bathe your
whole body. Presumably showers weren't as common as baths, so bathing you
just go straight in. But anyway, when you want to anoint, put
oil on your whole body, סך ראשו תחילה מפני שמלך על כל
איבריו. sach rosho techila mipnei shemelech al kol ivarav. You don't start
with other parts, you start with the head because the head is
the king of all. Now I want to say that to some
degree this seems very like a little silly, as Michael said, like
this is הלכה, Halacha, which shoe you put on first? I mean
and
what's exactly the הלכה, Halacha, what הלכה Halacha does this fall under,
why should I be doing this? and that obviously is a lot
of people's reactions to it. I will say that this is something
that I did since a young age and very מקפיד makpid on
everything written in the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. So you put your
shoes on in an order, you take a shower, first you do
your head, then you do the right, then you do the left
exactly like this גמרא Gemara says. And while in some sort of
rationalistic way it might not make so much sense, first of all
some people give them kabbalistic explanation. The right is רחמים, Rachamim, the
שמאל smol is דין. Din. So you want to show that even
though there's an aspect of דין Din in the world it should
be subsumed under רחמים Rachamim so you favor the right over the
left. Anyway, I wanted to read you a מאירי Meiri I found
which gives an explanation which to me resonated very much in terms
of how I experience this
religiously. I don't have a copy of this, you'll just listen to
this. He says like this. He says
תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, interesting he frames it about תלמידי חכמים, talmidei
chachamim, not like this is being said for
everybody. כל מעשיהם פונים אל תכלית אחת אפילו בשעה שעוסקים בצרכי גופם.
kol ma'aseihem panim el tachlit achat afilu besha'at she'osekim betzorchei gufam. So
they're always thinking about one thing, basically God. It's a God consciousness
even when they are dealing with just their physical bodily needs. לבם
פונה לכוונת עבודת השם. libam poneh lekavanat avodat Hashem. Even when they're
dealing with their bodily needs they're always thinking about serving God. כראיה
דכשנועל מנעליו מברך שעשה לי כל צרכי. keraya d'keshenoel minalav mevarech she'asa
li kol tzorki. First of all when you put on your shoes,
we do all of these ברכות השחר Birkhot HaShachar all together, but
according to the גמרא Gemara when you put on your shoes you
make a ברכה, bracha, שעשה לי כל צרכי. she'asa li kol tzorki.
You appreciate how the ability to have shoes is not to be
taken for granted and the gift of God that He's given us
the ability to stand, to walk, to have shoes on our feet
and you make the ברכה bracha שעשה לי כל צרכי, she'asa li
kol tzorki, so you're thinking about God when you're putting on your
shoes. שיתברך שמו, sheyitbarach shemo, even when the order you're putting them
on, נועל של ימין תחילה כדי להעלות על לב שבכל דבר ראוי
להימלך ולחלוק כבוד לכל מי שהוא דרך ימין. noel shel yemin techila
kedei lehaalot al lev shebechol davar ra'uy lehimalach velachlok kavod lekol mi
shehu derech yemin. ימין Yemin for him symbolizes like the right path
as opposed to the wrong path so it symbolizes you should always
prefer those that are making the right choices in life rather than
the wrong ones. But the point is that it's about God consciousness
and I think that that to me is very profound that even
if the most trivial of things, the order you cut your fingernails,
the order you put on your shoes, the way in which you
bathe your
body, it could just feel like some people could experience that as
the burden of הלכה Halacha and maybe it just becomes too weighty
and that's true that for some people it's
a challenge, an issue that הלכה Halacha feels like it's too dictating
and too controlling, but it also could just create a sense of
like you're always thinking about having a God consciousness in even the
small things that you do.
Yes, I was actually taught that this is one of the most
important הלכות Halakhot in the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. Really? For some
and for some of these reasons and because a lot of the
other stuff there it's obvious why it might be important to keep
שבת Shabbat or to keep kosher or to keep the property laws
but this is not so obvious and we're accepting the yoke of
heaven, we're expanding our God consciousness by being commanded.
יישר כוח, Yashar koach, very much that same point.
Yes, I really want to thank you because I'm sitting here saying
and we lost the Temple because of this and we fight with
each other and then you really did something for me personally by
reading that piece.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Okay, so very interesting. Okay, so
very interesting, right, where the conversation has gone and, you know, having
הלכות Halachas about these areas, but I very much appreciate the comments
and I do think that it can really become a very powerful
type of a religious experience to be thinking about that.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues, ולא בתפילין, v’lo bitfillin, it's going
to be a fun דף daf today. So we move from shoes
and the order of shoes to the תפילין. Tefillin. You cannot wear
תפילין Tefillin on שבת, Shabbat, but if you do, you're not חייב,
chayav, it's not like carrying. So אמר רב ספרא, Amar Rav Safra,
לא תימא אליבא דמאן דאמר שבת לאו זמן תפילין. lo teima aliba
d’man d’amar Shabbat lav zman tefillin. The problem here wearing תפילין Tefillin
is not just according to the opinion that you're not supposed to
wear תפילין Tefillin on שבת, Shabbat, because שבת Shabbat is itself a
sign and therefore you're not supposed to have another sign, and שבת
Shabbat is not a time that you are not just not obligated
but not supposed to wear תפילין. Tefillin. That's obvious according to that
approach, you should not be wearing it.
אלא אפילו למאן דאמר שבת זמן תפילין, Ella afilu l’man d’amar Shabbat
zman tefillin, even according to the opinion that you do wear תפילין
Tefillin on שבת Shabbat and there was that opinion, לא יצא, lo
yetzei, you still should not wear תפילין Tefillin outdoors. Why? דילמא אתי
לאתויי ברשות הרבים, Dilma ati l’atuyei b’reshut harabim, because you'll be wearing
your תפילין Tefillin in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, so what? And רש"י,
Rashi, oh, so you'll come to carry it in רשות הרבים. reshut
harabim. How are you come to carry it in רשות הרבים? reshut
harabim? So רש"י Rashi says, and the גמרא Gemara will sort of
address this in a minute, you'll have to go to the bathroom.
And the bathrooms were outdoors. You'll go to the bathroom, you'll take
off your תפילין. Tefillin. You'll take off your תפילין Tefillin and then
you won't put them on right away and you'll carry them. So
therefore, even if you're allowed to wear your תפילין Tefillin on שבת,
Shabbat, don't wear them outdoors. That's one read of the משנה. Mishnah.
And it's a rabbinic issue. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואיכא דמתני
לה אסיפא. v’ika d’matni lah aseifa.
Some, yes, if you left, presumably you left your home, so isn't
that when you take them off outside in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim,
that's violation?
No, but if you're right outside the בית הכסא, beit hakisei, you
take them off, you leave them right where you're standing and you
walk in. But where did you come from in the first place?
But you're wearing them, right, the assumption is, thank you, the assumption
is that wearing them is like a type of clothing, right? Oh,
okay. Right, right, I'm sorry, I did not make that clear. So
if שבת זמן תפילין, Shabbat zman tefillin, thank you, so if שבת
זמן תפילין, Shabbat zman tefillin, then it's not just okay to wear
them, but the assumption is that then it's a form of clothing
or it's a form of things you wear, and therefore carrying is
not an issue, but you still are rabbinically not allowed to because
you would come to take it off. But now we get to
the interesting flip side. So it says like this, ואיכא דמתני לה
אסיפא. v’ika d’matni lah aseifa. Some say this discussion about is it
שבת זמן תפילין Shabbat zman tefillin or not is on the end
of the משנה Mishnah and not our משנה, Mishnah, but a later
משנה Mishnah that says, oh no, I'm sorry, yes, the end of
our משנה, Mishnah, ואם יצא אינו חייב חטאת, v’im yatza eino chayav
chatat, that if you did wear the תפילין, Tefillin, you have not,
you're not obligated a חטאת, sin offering, you did not biblically violate
שבת. Shabbat. Okay. So אמר רב ספרא, Amar Rav Safra, לא תימא
אליבא דמאן דאמר שבת זמן תפילין, lo teima aliba d’man d’amar Shabbat
zman tefillin, this isn't now, this is a big חידוש, chiddush, this
isn't only according to the one that says שבת Shabbat is a
time of תפילין, Tefillin, so therefore by wearing them you didn't violate
שבת Shabbat biblically, because that's like some clothing or something you wear.
אלא אפילו למאן דאמר שבת לאו זמן תפילין, Ella afilu l’man d’amar
Shabbat lav zman tefillin, even according to the approach that שבת Shabbat
is a time that you're not allowed to wear תפילין, Tefillin, הוא
אינו חייב חטאת, hu eino chayav chatat, you are not חייב chayav
if you wear תפילין Tefillin outdoors, even though you're not allowed to
be wearing it. מאי טעמא, Mai ta’ama, from a תפילין Tefillin point,
you would think it's, how can you call it clothing? You're not
allowed to be wearing it. No, you haven't violated, why? דרך מלבוש
עבידתיה, Derech malbush avidtei, because it's the way of wearing. You wore
it rather than carrying it. Now, what does this mean? You know,
this sounds like anything that you are wearing as opposed to holding
and carrying is not considered biblical carrying. As long as it's somehow
being worn by me, even if it's not clothing, it's not a
problem. Now, the problem with that is, is that we know from
other גמרות, Gemaras, earlier גמרות Gemaras and later גמרות Gemaras and משניות,
Mishnayot, that's not true. For example, one case we had was the
woman wearing the signet ring, where it said that that is carrying
and it's a biblical violation of שבת. Shabbat. Now, she's wearing it,
she's not having it in her hand, she has it on her
finger, but somehow when we say no, that's considered not the norms
or it's not jewelry, it's not clothing, it's a way of carrying
a signet ring and therefore, sorry, you violated. So you see just
because you wear it doesn't get you off the hook. So what
does this mean that תפילין Tefillin are דרך מלבוש? derech malbush? So
the, right, so what the ריטב"א Ritva says is, he says the
question is, how do we look at it during the rest of
the week? So by תפילין, Tefillin, the rest of the week, it,
right, when you wear it, it's considered to be something that's worn.
Now, that's itself a חידוש chiddush we'll get back to. But by
a signet ring, when a woman is wearing a signet ring, since
that's not normally for a woman jewelry or whatever practice, it's seen
as she's carrying her ring on her finger. It's seen as a
way of conveyance, it's not seen as a type of a wearing.
Whereas תפילין Tefillin during the rest of the week is seen as
wearing. And therefore, even on שבת Shabbat when you're not allowed to,
it's still defined as clothing, whereas the signet ring is always defined
as just carrying it on your finger and not defined as clothing.
But I have to say it is pretty strange. I mean, it
is true, you talk about wearing your תפילין, Tefillin, but you know,
like conceptually, do you think of it as clothing? Do you think
of it as jewelry? You know, do you think of it as
just like a way you have a ritual object on your body?
But I guess the difference still is... It's not about conveyance. As
opposed to the idea of the signet ring, the idea is that
you want it with you so you can use it somewhere else,
whereas תפילין, tefillin, it's you want it on your body and therefore,
it's not about moving it and conveying it from one place and
therefore it's considered to be a type of clothing and if that's
the way it is during the week, that's the way it is
on שבת. Shabbat. Yes.
So would there be that distinction between men and women for תפילין?
tefillin?
That's an interesting question. That's right. That could very well be. Just
like the signet ring, you have that difference, presumably you have that
difference by the תפילין tefillin as well. It's a very good point.
Yes.
I'm not understanding. Just
שבת Shabbat and תפילין tefillin can be different types of signs. Why
do you have to say the one contradicts the other, that you
know.
All right. You know what? So that's whether שבת Shabbat is זמן
תפילין zman tefillin is a whole סוגיא sugya עירובין, Eruvin, which we'll
get to, like in four months or something, but I think that's
where it's majorly discussed. We're not going to get into that now.
Yes.
Explain, I must have missed this, how does the signet ring get
used on שבת? Shabbat?
No, it doesn't, but how would we look at it during the
week? So if a man's wearing a signet ring during the week,
we look at it as a type of a jewelry, it looks
nice on him or whatever. Women normally would not wear this, you
know, it wouldn't be seen of as jewelry so it would be
seen as a way of carrying the ring from one place to
another. So because how you look at it during the week. Because
of the custom of the time. Because of the custom and the
norms of the time that men would wear signet rings and women
would not. So if a woman has a signet ring on her
finger, it would be perceived of as carrying it on her finger,
not wearing it.
So essentially, a woman shouldn't be wearing a signet ring at all.
You mean because of like בגד איש beged ish or something like
that?
Because if you think about it, she's not supposed to be wearing
it during the week and then she can't wear it on שבת,
Shabbat, when should she wear it?
Well, no, it's not she's not supposed to be wearing it in
the week, it wouldn't be within the, it's not within the societal
norms to be wearing it during the week. So it's not she's
not supposed to. Okay, but anyway, but that so it is, it
is again hard to always exactly define these lines, you know, that
certain things are worn and are said and the rabbis sort of
say, oh, that's considered, you know, not jewelry, not clothing, that's carrying
and here the תפילין tefillin is considered to be a type of
clothing. We'll see a little bit more of this as we continue.
Now we get to the perhaps most fascinating part of this דף,
daf, which is the wearing of amulets. ולא בקמיע שאינו מן המומחה.
V'lo b'kame'a she'eino min hamumcheh. You cannot wear an amulet not from
a non-expert, but if you did you're not חייב חטאת chayav chatat
and you are allowed even לכתחילה lechatchila to wear an amulet from
an expert. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רב
פפא, Amar Rav Papa, says Rav Papa, לא תימא עד דמומחה גברא
ומומחה קמיע. Lo teima ad demumcheh gavra umumcheh kame'a. In order to
allow you לכתחילה lechatchila to wear this amulet, it doesn't have to
be that both the writer of the amulet has been shown to
be an expert and has been tested and the amulet itself has
been tested. So what would be the difference? So there's a huge
amount of תוספות Tosafot on this to try and figure out the
exact specifics, which I'll just give you רש"י'ס Rashi's explanation although there
are obvious questions you'll ask. But anyway, so the מומחה, mumcheh, the
amulet being proven expert is not this physical amulet, that's the way
תוספות Tosafot reads it, it means this particular type of an incantation
or whatever they would write on the amulet. So if you know
three different people have used the same incantation for three different sick
people and it's been effective, you know this is an effective incantation.
So the amulet has been tested. On the other hand, if I,
the amulet writer, have written three different types of amulets for three
different people with three different illnesses and they've all worked, then you
know that I can you know I'm trusted in any amulet I
write. So I've been proven trustworthy. So he says you don't need
both me to be the writer to be trustworthy and the amulet
to be trustworthy and tested, אלא כיון דמומחה גברא אע"ג דלא מומחה
קמיע. ela keivan demumcheh gavra af al gav delo mumcheh kame'a.
As long as the
writer has been tested, then even if the amulet has not. It
seems like certainly if the amulet has been tested and you're using
the same type of amulet that's worked for other people, that's certainly.
But even without having tested this particular amulet, if the writer has
been tested, you can wear his amulet לכתחילה lechatchila on שבת. Shabbat.
דיקא נמי, Deika nami, this is also going to be inferred, דקתני,
d'katani, ולא בקמיע בזמן שאינה מן המומחה, v'lo b'kame'a bizman she'einah min
hamumcheh, and not with a קמיע kame'a when it's not from a
מומחה, mumcheh, from an expert. So the issue is who is who
is writing it. ולא קתני בזמן שאינה מומחה. V'lo katani bizman she'einah
mumcheh. It doesn't say that the amulet has been tested, a proven
amulet or non-proven, it says an amulet from a proven person. So
that suffices that the person has been proven to be a good,
you know, an effective writer of amulets even if the amulet itself
has not. שמע מינה, Shema mina, that is a good proof. Now
we are going to discuss, I know everybody's question is, well, there's
two of them. Number one, how did the rabbis believe in amulets?
Which, okay, we'll bracket that for now. Everybody sort of did. And
but the other question is, right, you know, if they believed in
its efficaciousness then okay, we can understand maybe they'll allow you to
wear it. But like how would that translate, you know, nowadays and
how do we deal with this type of a גמרא Gemara not
just with their particular belief in amulets? רמב"ם Rambam says multiple times
per but often about witchcraft, but particularly in the מורה נבוכים Moreh
Nevuchim specifically about amulets, that it's all שקר וכזב sheker v'chazav and
so on. So how do you deal, you know, with this type
of So I will talk about that I'll talk about that in
a minute, just a small technical point though that presumably the difference,
two important points to realize before we get to the challenges of
amulets themselves. Number one is, so what's the difference if it's an
expert or non-expert amulet? Presumably if it's only rabbinic, biblically it's considered
not a problem. So it seems to be if the old issue,
at least the way the גמרא Gemara would explain it, although it
doesn't say it explicitly, although it implies it, that if it's a
non-expert amulet you're maybe not so hesitant to take it off. And
therefore again it's a concern that you might take it off and
carry it, whereas if it's an expert one, so you know you
better can't remove it, it needs to protect you, and therefore there's
no concern of carrying. But what the common denominator is is that
assuming they believe this amulet was efficacious, they did believe this amulet
was efficacious, it's not considered carrying on שבת. Shabbat. And we will
see later that a whole other series of various bandages and things
that are done for the health of the body are also not
considered carrying on שבת. Shabbat. So it falls into that category. And
that's interesting because if you think about it, it's not a garment.
It's not, I mean maybe this amulet you could say is a
type of a jewelry, but there's a whole list of things, bandages
are not a garment, okay. It's not a garment, it's not jewelry,
why is it not a שבת Shabbat problem? So you could try
to argue it's a type of a garment. The purpose of a
garment is to protect the body. This is preserving the health of
the body, it's a type of a garment. But it could also
be that maybe even if it's not a garment and not jewelry,
something that as we've seen is considered to be, you know, worn
or something that's seen to be like attached to the body, a
part of the body, you know, somehow an addendum to the body
is not carrying. Again, maybe the idea is less to describe something
as clothing and jewelry
and more to ask the question of are you conveying it on
your body or are you wearing it, right? So if you have
a ring on your finger that you're using as a seal and
the signet ring the real point is to convey it, okay, it's
not that you want to be wearing it, whereas these things you
want them on your body at all times, and therefore it's not
considered carrying. So that's an important issue which we'll see more of,
the general things like bandages and other types of things that are
there for the health of the body are actually not considered to
be carrying and the amulet is one of them. We will discuss
in a minute how we deal with this whole issue of amulets,
yes.
So in addition to the issue of believing in amulets at all,
they're not taking into account, first of all, they're not taking account
that it may be three out of three versus three out of
three thousand.
What do you mean? You mean maybe you just got lucky?
Yeah, and they actually do consider denominators when they talk about the
definition of a plague in מסכת תענית. Masechet Taanit.
Right. Okay, so רש״י Rashi tells us, tries to work this in,
and you know, we'll discuss in the גמרא Gemara how many different
ways it's been tested.
And the other thing is, they could have tested it using the
method that's in the first chapter of דניאל, Daniel, where they actually
compared it to something else.
What do you mean, they did a placebo?
Yeah, there was a control group. But I've never seen anywhere in
the בבלי Bavli where
they've actually ignored a
biblical precedent ever.
I don't know what to say about that. Okay.
Yeah. If it's a non-expert amulet but you made it like really
nice, then it could be transformed into jewelry?
You could, you could, but that's not the point. Yeah.
Do we have any examples of what would be written on these
amulets?
So in the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara does sometimes talk about
various לחשים, lachashim, incantations. Not clear to me if the גמרא Gemara
explicitly identifies what was written in the amulets, but we actually do
have a lot of amulets from the ancient world, you know, and
Jewish amulets and things that have, yeah, verses written in them and
other types of manipulating of letters and there's actually I can send
out a link to a site that actually has a lot of
that data in it.
Yes. They just found one a couple weeks ago in Austria.
Really? Okay, so now let's take a look though because I have
some important things I want to discuss about this. So first we're
just going to discuss this גמרא Gemara about how to prove whether
it's tested or not and okay, we'll just see it. תנו רבנן:
Tanu Rabbanan: איזהו קמיע מומחה, Eizehu kameia mumcheh, what is a proven
קמיע, kameia, a proven amulet? כל שריפא ושנה ושלש. Kol sheripa veshana
veshillesh. Anything that's healed once, twice, and three times. So it could
be the same person, could be different people, but it's healed the
same sickness three times. אחד קמיע של כתב ואחד קמיע של עיקרין,
Echad kameia shel ketav ve'echad kameia shel ikkarin, whether it is one
of writing, you have certain various types of incantations or other things
written in it, or whether it has various types of herbs in
it. So maybe it's actually natural type of a healing, it's all
the same. אחד חולה שיש בו סכנה ואחד חולה שאין בו סכנה,
Echad choleh sheyesh bo sakanah ve'echad choleh she'ein bo sakanah, whether it,
the person has a risk of life or not a risk of
life. Either way, we're not allowing this because of the risk of
life, we're allowing this because it's considered to be a form of
wearing something. לא שנכפה, Lo shenichpeh, and not only, רש״י Rashi reads
this as not only, not only if somebody has already been sick
and this is there to protect them from future or to heal
them. נכפה Nichpeh actually means epilepsy, specifically talking about that, that was
a big concern. אלא שלא יכפה, Ella shelo yichpeh, it's enough that
a person is concerned that he might fall sick. רש״י Rashi says
maybe he has this problem in his family, that is also a
legitimate enough reason to be wearing one. and it becomes an issue
of clothing and not carrying. וקושר ומתיר אפילו ברשות הרבים, Vekosher umatir
afilu birishut harabim,
you can undo it and do it again even in רשות הרבים,
Reshut harabim, presumably it means without a biblical knot on שבת, Shabbat,
okay, but but it means like somehow specifically adjusting you can stand
in your place and adjust it. Okay, which seems to be like
again since a lot of these issues were concerns that you'll come
to carry it that seems to be giving you a good amount
of latitude maybe because again they really felt it was effective or
because and or because they believed that you will be so concerned
to remove not to have it off your body that we're not
concerned you will come to carry.
What about removal or
loose knot?
What? Why is it allowed? No, you're adjusting it, you're not taking
it off, you're adjusting it. ובלבד שלא יקשרנו, Uvilvad shelo yikshurenu,
but as long as you do not tie it בשיר ובטבעת Beshir
uvtabaat
on a bracelet or a ring. Why? ויצא בו ברשות הרבים Veyeitzei
bo birishut harabim and go out to רשות הרבים Reshut harabim משום
מראית העין Mishum mar'it ha-ayin because of the appearances. What are the
appearances? So רש״י Rashi says what it means is is that then
you're making it look like as Michael said you're wearing it as
a type of jewelry, but actually we're not allowing this as jewelry,
we're allowing this because it's something that's healing or protecting your health
and therefore again that's a particular category of things that are not
carrying, but to wear it tied to your bracelet making it like
jewelry then that is mis you know giving people misunderstandings about why
you're allowed to wear and that's not what this is about so
it's not jewelry. Yes but you're but this presumably was not something
that was sort of like the woman's signet ring was not something
that was worn as jewelry or acknowledged as a legitimate type of
jewelry. So therefore we don't want it to be looking like that's
what how it's being worn, it has to be worn as an
amulet. Okay. והתניא, Vehatanya, the גמרא Gemara says didn't we teach in
a ברייתא Braita איזו קמיע מומחה כל שריפא ג' בני אדם כאחד?
Eizo kamea mumche kol sheripa gimel bnei adam ke-echad? What is considered
an expert tested קמיע? Kamea? If it healed three people. So meaning
so not that the same not like the same meaning presumably רש״י
Rashi says three this is the way רש״י Rashi reads it three
different people whereas before we spoke about healing the same type of
problem three times. So the גמרא Gemara said לא קשיא הא למומחי
גברא הא למומחי קמיע. Lo kashya ha le-mumche gavra ha le-mumche kamea.
Are you trying to test the person or the קמיע? Kamea? If
it's the קמיע Kamea then it's the same thing three times. If
it's the person then it's three that he's healed three different people
with three different types of amulets. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa,
so רב פפא Rav Papa said פשיטא לי Pshita li it's obvious
to me תלת קמיעי לתלת גברי תלת תלתא זימני איתמחי גברא ואיתמחי
קמיע. Tlat kmeiei litlat gavrei tlat tlata zimni itmachi gavra ve-itmachi kamea.
You have one person that wrote three amulets to three different people
and he did this at three different times so three times three
times three yeah three different sicknesses so and each sickness has he
did for the same guy let's say three times. So now both
the person has been proven as an expert and this incantation has
been proven effective because each incantation worked for its disease three times
in a row and that means that even if written by another
person you have proven that this is an effective incantation. Okay so
that's both the person and the קמיע Kamea have been have been
proven. Now תלתא קמיעי לתלתא גברי חד חד זימנא Tlata kmeiei litlata
gavrei chad chad zimna
let's say it's three amulets for three different people and each one
only once for each person so in that case גברא איתמחי קמיע
לא איתמחי. Gavra itmachi kamea lo itmachi. The writer the you know
the person who was prescribing these קמיע Kameas he has been proven
that you know that he knows what he's doing effectively because he's
healed three different people under three different circumstances with three different incantations
or amulets but any one amulet has not been proven to always
work so therefore if another person wrote it you know not one
no one amulet has been proven three times you could not trust
it. חד קמיע לתלת גברי, Chad kamea litlat gavrei, if now
the flip if you had one קמיע Kamea written for one
קמיע Kamea written for three for three people קמיע איתמחי וגברא לא
איתמחי. Kamea itmachi vegavra lo itmachi.
So in that case it again this presumes that it is the
same sickness so a three one קמיע Kamea the same קמיע Kamea
the same
incantation for three different people then the incantation has proven effective but
not the writer because the writer you don't know he's only done
the same thing three times so all you know is the effectiveness
of the incantation so we have three times three both are proven
one times three or three times one depending on which way it's
going if it's the same thing for the same for the same
illness then it proves the effectiveness of the incantation if it's different
illnesses and different people and the same author then it proves the
effectiveness of the author and any one of those are sufficient for
wearing it on שבת. Shabbat. So בעי רב פפא, Bei Rav Papa,
so רב פפא Rav Papa asked תלתא קמיעי לחד גברא מאי? Tlata
kmeiei le-chad gavra mai?
Let's say one person got sick three different types of illness and
you wrote him three different incantations okay so what do we say
now? קמיע ודאי לא איתמחי Kamea vadai lo itmachi
there's no question that any one incantation has not been proven because
it was
three different
incantations. Has he been proven to always be effective because he, you
know, he prescribed three different amulets, three different circumstances and it always
worked? The question is, because it's always for one person, או לא
איתמחי. o lo itmchi. מי אמרינן mi amrinan do we say הא
אסי ליה, ha assi lei, look, three different things, it's always been
effective, so you see you can trust him? או דילמא, o dilma,
מזלא דהאי גברא הוא דקא מקבל
כתבא, mazla d'hai gavra hu d'ka mekabbel ktava, maybe it's this person,
the sick person, that for him the writing, the prescription is very
effective? So we don't know, maybe he wouldn't be effective for other
people. So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, we don't know the
answer to that. Now, I will stop now, we're going to do
a little bit more about this, but to talk a minute about
or more than a minute about this question about the effectiveness of
these קמיעות. kameiot. So מאירי Meiri just to say right at the
outset basically tries to ascribe this to a type of a psychosomatic
thing, that people who believed it was effective, and therefore, and if
the whole difference between if it's expert or not expert is are
we afraid they'll come to take it off? So then it really
doesn't matter whether they really are effective or not. If they believe
it's expert, they won't take it off. If they're suspicious, if they're
not so certain it's expert, they'll come to take it off. And
that basically says we're allowing this basically because people believe that it
worked and that would be sufficient to define it as wearing and
not carrying. But I wanted to show you very quickly here, we'll
pass this around this way and this around this way, about some
discussion here in the רמב"ם Rambam and elsewhere. We don't have time
to do this in full but we have a little extra time.
What? The Hawthorne?
Yeah, that if you're, I thought it's called the placebo effect.
That's a placebo effect. Hawthorne effect is if you're being studied at
all you're going to do better whether there's a placebo.
Yeah, but if you believe it works.
No, no, no.
But not for the epilepsy which they mentioned.
Yeah, just go in opposite directions, just go in opposite directions, there
are some different pages. I want to start with the one, the
Bar Ilan wasn't working last night so I wasn't able to get
everything in the nice font here, but anyway, you'll have to, but
I want to start with the one here that's the actual like
the printed page, you know, the one that's all the same font.
So here's a רמב"ם. Rambam. It says, okay, here's the רמב"ם Rambam
if you look at the top in הלכות שבת פרק יט הלכה
יג, Hilchos Shabbos Perek Yud Tes Halacha Yud Gimmel, the רמב"ם Rambam
quoting another משנה Mishna which we'll see, יוצא אדם בקיסם שבשיניו, yotzei
adam b'keisam she'b'shinav, you can have a toothpick in your teeth, ובסנדלו
לרשות הרבים ואם נפל לא יחזיר, u'v'sandalo l'reshus ha'rabim v'im nafal lo
yachzir, ובמוך ובספוג שעל גבי המכה, u'v'moch u'v'sfog she'al gabi ha'maka, a
bandage on a wound, and he goes on and on. He says
יוצא בקליפת השום ובקליפת הבצל שעל המכה, yotzei b'klipas ha'shum u'v'klipas ha'batzal
she'al ha'maka, you can wear certain types of garlic or onion on
your
wound, and goes on and on about different types of things. And
then at the last line he says you can wear ביצת החרגול
ובשן השועל ובמסמר הצלוב. beitzas ha'chargol u'v'shein ha'shual u'v'masmer ha'tzaluv. You can
wear like a tooth of an ox and a nail from a
crucifixion and these
things, ובכל דבר שתולין אותו משום רפואה, u'v'chol davar she'tolin oso mishum
refuah, anything that you wear for the sake of healing, even though
this clearly seems to be some type of
superstitious type of a thing, והוא שיאמרו הרופאים שהוא מועיל, v'hu she'yomru
ha'rofim she'hu mo'il, if the doctors say it's effective. And then in
יד yud daled he has archetypes of the קמיע. kameia. יוצאים בקמיע
מומחה, yotzim b'kameia mumcheh, an expert one, and what is it? It
healed three people, dot dot dot dot dot. And then he says
the second line here, ואם יצא בקמיע שאינו מומחה פטור מפני שהוציאו
דרך מלבוש. v'im yatza b'kameia she'eino mumcheh patur mipnei she'hotzio derech malbush.
Even if it wasn't an expert, it's okay because you're wearing it
as opposed to carrying it. Now, just for the sake of time
I'll just sort of summarize the next thing. The משנה יומא Mishna
Yoma speaks about a type of a healing that doing on יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, feeding somebody some the liver of a rabid dog.
And the רמב"ם Rambam says we don't go by this, because the
third paragraph the רמב"ם Rambam says, וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, where it
says הרמב"ם בפירוש המשנה, ha'Rambam b'peirush ha'Mishna, the second line, וחכמים אומרים
אין עוברין על מצוה אלא בריפוי בלבד, v'Chachamim omrim ein overin al
mitzvah ela b'ripui bilvad, you can only transgress like a mitzvah, meaning
there יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, because it would be שבת, Shabbos, if
it's a type of a healing, type of a treatment, שהוא דבר
ברור שההגיון והנסיון הפשוט מחייבים אותו. she'hu davar barur she'ha'higayon v'ha'nisayon ha'pashut
mechayvim oso. If it is something that rationally makes sense. אבל הריפוי
בסגולה לא. aval ha'ripui b'sgulah lo. But doing it with these types
of סגולות, sgulot, I don't know an English translation for סגולות, sgulot,
well you cannot do to violate יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, לפי שעניינם
חלוש לא יחייבו ההגיון. lefi she'inyanam chalush lo yachivu ha'higayon. The reason
for them is very weak, they're not, cannot be rationally explained, ונסיונו
רחוק, v'nisyono rachok, and it's very hard to prove its effectiveness. והוא
טענה מן הטועים בזה וזה כלל גדול. v'hu ta'ana min ha'to'im baze
v'ze klal gadol. Okay, fine. So then he says you cannot use
it. Right. So what do you do as a fact? He said
you can wear this crucifixion. Okay. Now this is a passage from
מורה נבוכים Moreh Nevuchim where he basically says, just read the English
translation at the bottom. It wasn't written in Hebrew, it was written
in Arabic anyway, so both of these are translations. It is not
inconsistent this actually speaks about the nonsense of amulets. It is not
inconsistent that a nail of the gallows and the tooth of a
fox have been permitted to be used as cures, for these things
have been considered in those days as facts established by experiment. So
for them they thought it was effective. They served as cures in
the same manner as the hanging of peony over a person epileptic
fits, or application of dog refuse to the swellings of the throat,
ever try that? And the vapors and blah blah blah. For the
law permits as medicine everything that has been verified by experiment, although
not to be explained by
analogy. The above-named cures are permitted in the same way of the
application of purgatives. Now what is he saying? Is he saying that
for the Rabbis it was effective, that that explains why they allowed
it, but we know better? So if that's true, why is he
ruling in משנה תורה Mishneh Torah that you can do it? And
if he so is he saying that it really is effective? What
exactly is he saying? So the רשב"א Rashba here in a תשובה
Teshuvah so the רדב"ז Radvaz first of all which is on one
of these pages which we won't read, who was a ראשון Rishon
who has a whole section of his תשובות Teshuvot that explains the
רמב"ם Rambam and he says, yeah, you really can't use anything that
is not medically sound, and when the רמב"ם Rambam allows it it's
because it anyway would all be rabbinic carrying, it wouldn't be a
biblical violation. Why would it be a rabbinic violation? Because it's like
שינוי shinui you'd carry it around your body, you're not carrying it
in your hand, so at most it's only a rabbinic concern, and
that's why we allow it because of psychological issues, but really we
would never allow you to violate a biblical issue. The רשב"א Rashba
doesn't understand, like he says the רמב"ם Rambam needs to make up
his mind. He says, הנה שאסר לנו, Hineh she-asar lanu,
talking about the רמב"ם, Rambam, he forbade for us, אפילו מה שיש
בו תועלת מצד הסגולה חוץ ממה שגוזר העניין הטבעי. afilu mah she-yesh
bo to'elet mitzad ha-segulah chutz mima she-gozer ha-inyan ha-tiv'i. He says, ah,
if it doesn't make sense by science and nature, you can't use
it. ונשוב ונספר, ve-nashuv ve-nesaper, so fine, if you want to say
that, go and make forbidden מסמר הצלוב, masmer ha-tzaluv, so go make
forbidden the nail of the crucifixion because of דרכי האמורי, darkhei ha-Emori,
now it should fall in the category of things that are superstitious.
לא ידענו איזה נקח בידינו למעשה. lo yadanu eizeh nikach be-yadeinu le-ma'aseh.
So make up your mind, רמב"ם, Rambam, do you want us to
only use the ones that make sense, or do you want to
let us use the nail of the crucifix of the crucifixion? So
he says, למעשה מדברי הרב או ההיתר כמסמר
הצלוב, le-ma'aseh mi-divrei ha-Rav o ha-heter ke-masmer ha-tzaluv, either you'll allow us
to use the nails and say don't demand that it be a
logical
thing, או מה שאסר משום דרכי האמורי. o mah she-asar mishum darkhei
ha-Emori. Now he
says, ואולי יאמר הרב שאפילו מה שתלה בספריהם לסגולה לא נאמין, ve-ulai
yomar ha-Rav she-afilu mah she-talah be-sifreihem lise-gulah lo na'amin, don't trust the
non-Jews what they say is a
סגולה, segulah, לפי שעניינם לתועלת ההבל, lefi she-inyanam le-to'elet ha-hevel, אבל מה
שחכמים, aval mah she-chachamim, but what the Rabbis say is a סגולה,
segulah, maybe that we can believe, but he basically says I don't
get what the רמב"ם Rambam is trying to say. And the next
paragraph he basically says, and what anyway does the רמב"ם Rambam mean
that it makes sense? Makes sense according to who? According to the
Greek rationalists? So why should that determine for us what makes sense
or doesn't make sense? And the רמ- and he basically goes ahead
and he says we can trust all these סגולות. segulahs סגולות was
very widespread in the Middle Ages, we can totally trust them, forget
the רמב"ם, Rambam, he's being too much of a rationalist and anyway
he's inconsistent. If you look at the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, the
שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says, מי שנשכו עקרב או מותר ללחוש עליו
אפילו בשבת, mi she-nashcho akrav o mutar le-lachosh alav afilu be-Shabbat,
you can say an incantation over a scorpion bite, ואף על פי
שאין הדבר מועיל כלל, ve-af al pi she-ein ha-davar mo'il klal, even
though it's not effective, he's here influenced by the רמב"ם, Rambam, הואיל
ומסוכן הוא התירו, ho'il u-mesukan hu hitiru, today שלא תטורף דעתו עליו.
she-lo titoraf da'ato alav.
They allowed it so that he would not to calm him down.
A psycholog- a psycho-sm- not psychosomatic. What? It has a psychological effect.
Right, it has a psychological effect and therefore it's allowed. He doesn't
apply this to wearing the amulets, but presumably you could extend the
argument. Very famous הגר"א Gra on this. And the הגר"א Gra says,
הרמב"ם, ha-Rambam, quoting the רמב"ם, Rambam, וכן כתב פירוש המשנה, ve-khein katav
Perush ha-Mishnah, אבל כל הבאים אחריו חלקו עליו, aval kol ha-ba'im acharav
chalku alav, שהרי הרבה לחשים נאמרו בגמרא. she-harei harbeh lachashim ne'emru ba-Gemara.
Many, you know, what do you mean it's not effective? The גמרא
Gemara has all a lot of incantations. The גמרא Gemara took it
very seriously. והוא, ve-hu, the רמב"ם, Rambam, נמשך אחר הפילוסופיא, nimshach achar
ha-filosofia, and
he was influenced by the treif Greek philosophy, good for Chanukah, וכן
כתב שכשפים ושמות ולחשים שדים וקמיעות הכל הוא שקר. ve-khein katav she-keshafim
ve-shemot ve-lachashim shedim u-kemi'ot ha-kol hu sheker.
So he said that they were all false. אבל כבר היכו אותו
על קדקדו, aval kvar hiku oto al kodkodo, but people have beat
him over the head, שהרי מצינו הרבה בגמרא, she-harei matzinu harbeh ba-Gemara,
there's many of these etc. and then three lines from the bottom
he says, והפילוסופיא הטתו, ve-ha-filosofia hittatu,
the philosophy is what led him astray, ברוב לקחו לפרש הגמרא, be-rov
lekacho lefaresh ha-Gemara, it's חס ושלום, chas ve-shalom, איני מאמין בהם, eini
ma'amin ba-hem, ולא מהם, ve-lo me-hem, ולא מהמונם, ve-lo me-hamonam, אלא כל
הדברים הם כפשוטם. ela kol ha-devarim hem ki-fshatam. חס ושלום chas ve-shalom
we should be influenced by the Greek rationalist philosophy and all of
these things are true. So somebody once famously said, the רמב"ם Rambam
wrote there's no such thing as שדים shedim and then all the
שדים shedim disappeared. Then the הגר"א Gra wrote his comment, no, he
got it wrong, and then all the שדים shedim came back. So
that's the הגר"א. Gra. Yeah, that's very interesting.
I know because he really was into- he was into science, but
he was also a mystic. We tend to think only חסידים Chasidim
were mystics, but...
Where does רמב"ם Rambam say that it's there though? ...that it's אסור,
assur,
that it's permissible?
Yes, but the גר"א Gra doesn't like the reason why he's saying
it's permitted, to attribute it all to a psychological cure rather than
really being effective. He doesn't like this reframing of it as psychological.
They've been considered as facts established by
experiment,
so that's not psychological.
Well, that's the question. Maybe did the רמב"ם... Rambam... did right, the
רמב"ם Rambam said that's what the Rabbis thought, so that's the question,
did the רמב"ם Rambam actually think... maybe one way of explaining the
רמב"ם, Rambam, the רמב"ם Rambam doesn't say this psychological, maybe one way
of explaining the רמב"ם Rambam is maybe he thought some of these
actually have been proven. So I want to end by making two
points. First of all, the ברכי יוסף, Birkei Yosef, which I won't
read inside but I would highly recommend, is a question was asked
about... somebody had been tested that when people would drink poison, he
would write a certain incantation or whatever and they would spit up
the poison and they'd get better. Maybe if he stuck it in
their throat in a particular way it was effective. But anyway, and
somebody drank poison on שבת Shabbat and the Rabbi was מתיר matir
this person to write the incantation on שבת Shabbat because of פיקוח
נפש pikuach nefesh and it was effective, and he goes into a
whole discussion of will we allow something that makes no rational sense,
a type of a רפואה, refuah, to violate שבת? Shabbat? And he
goes back and forth on that. The ציץ אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer has
a similar question: can you send a telegram to a צדיק tzaddik
to pray for you on שבת? Shabbat? To pray for someone חולה
שיש בו סכנה.
choleh
she-yesh bo sakanah.
Maybe even write explicitly, do a מלאכה דאורייתא. melachah de-oraita. How much
do we believe in these cures or not to violate a מלאכה
דאורייתא melachah de-oraita is a big question. And a lot of it
is about how we deal with not the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא
Gemara believed it was effective. But how the רמב"ם Rambam as a
rationalist was able on the one hand to say it's not effective
and on the other hand to פסקן pasken the גמרא. Gemara. I
will tell you that an interesting question that is not as extreme
as incantations and קמיעות kame'ot is like homeopathic and Eastern medicine. I
once had a case where somebody had something and they wanted... all
the normal cures didn't work and they wanted to do a homeopathic
cure, somebody recommended it, and it had to do... anyway, it
had basically was taking desiccated scorpion in a tea bag and running
hot water through it and drinking it. So that's like טעם ta'am
of a דבר האסור, davar ha-assur, right, of a scorpion. So anyway,
but you know, it was bad taste, and there's logic, and of
course, you know, I thought it was okay because of a חולה
choleh and various other reasons and it was a bad taste so
it wasn't a biblical concern. Anyway, so I consulted with a couple
of my colleagues and you know, one of them said, 'Yeah, if
they think it's a cure, that's fine.' And the other, actually Rabbi
Yehuda Herzl Henkin said, said like, 'What is this nonsense?' you know?
Hoo-wa!
So I said, I said, 'I don't understand, you think it's different
than any of the cures in the גמרא? Gemara? I mean, who
are we to take our Western medicine and to say that anything
that doesn't fit with Western medicine we're not willing to consider?' But
I think that there is a difference between, you know, homeopathic and
Eastern which actually has, you know, proven effective in some cases, and
just we don't understand it but it's proven effective, as opposed to
things like amulets which we at least tend to think are total
nonsense. Other people think they're no more nonsense than Eastern medicine, you
know, so it's very... raises very interesting questions. Yes.
We also have to remember that when they talk about proof, they're
not talking about proof in the same way we do. After the
first chapter of the Book of Daniel, the next experimental study with
a comparison group was in the 18th century.
Right, it wasn't with a comparison group. It was just that it
was effective many times.
Yeah, and this
is where you tend to forget all the times that it wasn't
effective, you focus on the ones that it was, and you don't
know about the psychosomatic... Right, I understand, I understand. But I'm just
saying... yes?
Does this guy have to have 100 percent hit rate or like
let's say it
works for 10 people
but like let's say next 15 people die?
Yeah, so תוספות Tosafot discusses that a little. Let's wrap this discussion
up. Back to the גמרא. Gemara. איבעיא להו: iba'u lehu: קמיעים, kame'im,
two dots, middle of ס"א עמוד ב. Samech Aleph Amud Bet. קמיעים,
kame'im, יש בהם משום קדושה או דילמא אין בהם משום קדושה? yesh
bahem mishum kedushah o dilma ein bahem mishum kedushah? Is there sanctity
to them? Now, why would you think such a thing? Because in
the קמיע kame'a they would write פסוקים pesukim very often, like רש"י
Rashi says, like you know, it says... what is it? כל המחלה
אשר שמתי במצרים לא אשים עליך כי אני ה' רופאך. kol ha-machalah
asher samti be-Mitzrayim lo asim alecha ki ani Hashem rofecha. So they
would actually write פסוקים pesukim and שם ה'. Shem Hashem. So does
it have קדושה kedushah or not?
So the גמרא Gemara says: למאי הלכתא? le-mai hilcheta?
For
what הלכה? halakhah? אילימא לאצולינהו מפני הדליקה, ileima le-atzuluninhu mipnei ha-dleikah, that
if there's a fire breaks out on שבת Shabbat are you allowed
to save them because you would do a rabbinic carrying in order
to protect them? There would be a discussion later on about that.
תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear: הברכות והקמיעים, ha-berachot ve-ha-kame'im, if
you have ברכות, berachot, like once רש"י Rashi says it means like
written down שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei and in another place רש"י Rashi
says it means like the מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyos, Zichronos, and Shofros
because I think the reason he says that was, well first of
all they didn't write too much down, they didn't have סידורים, siddurim,
but maybe this they wrote down because who could remember it, you
say it twice a year, but also because it had פסוקים, pesukim,
the מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות. Malchuyos, Zichronos, and Shofros. So you have these
ברכות... berachot... והקמיעין ve-Hakame'in or קמיעות, Kameiot, which would have God's name
and a פסוק pasuk in them. אף על פי שיש בהם אותיות,
Af al pi she-yesh bahem otiyot, although it has letters which means
God's name, ומעניינות הרבה שבתורה u-me-inyanot harbeh she-ba-Torah and many quotes of
the Torah, אין מצילין אותם מפני הדליקה. ein matzilin otam mipnei ha-dleika.
You cannot save them, you would not allow you, I mean you're
passive, you're not actively destroying it. We don't allow you to do
a rabbinic violation to protect them even though it has פסוקים psukim
and God's name, they are not ספרי קודש. sifrei kodesh. ונשרפין במקומם,
ve-nisrafin bimkomam, you let them burn in their place, you know, you
can't give them a full status as ספרי קודש sifrei kodesh although
they have פסוקים psukim written in them. Okay, so therefore that's the
answer, you don't save them. אלא הן גניזה. ela hen gniza. Okay,
fine, the question is, do you have to bury it, you know,
if you're throwing it out, do you have to or can you
just like destroy it? תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear, היה
כתוב על ידות הכלים ועל כרעי המיטה, haya katuv al yadot ha-keilim
ve-al kar'ei ha-mita, if there was God's name written on a handle
of a vessel or on a leg of a bed, יגוד, yigod,
so cut it off the place of God's name, ויגנזנו, ve-yignazenu, and
put it in גניזה. gniza. So if it's about גניזה, gniza, doesn't
matter, you know, where it's written. Any time you have God's name
or maybe a פסוק, pasuk, you have to put it in גניזה.
gniza. Doesn't matter if it's, so there's one question, do you call
the object כתבי קודש? kisvei kodesh? Do you call the object ספרי
קודש? sifrei kodesh? That we don't. Don't save them מפני הדליקה. mipnei
ha-dleika. There's another question of God's name or פסוק, pasuk, you wherever
it's written, you gotta cut it out and bury it. Okay, so
that's that answer, so that's the answer there is yes. אלא, ela,
so the גמרא Gemara says, ליכנס בהם לבית הכיסא. likanes bahem le-veit
ha-kisei. Here's my question: can you, when you're wearing your קמיע, kmeia,
can you go into the bathroom? Okay, because it's in a covered
pouch presumably, but it has God's name in it, could you walk
into the bathroom? So let's see, מאי? mai? יש בהם משום קדושה
ואסור, yesh bahem mishum kedusha ve-asur, is there קדושה kedusha and it's
forbidden? או דילמא אין בהם קדושה ושרי, o dima ein bahem kedusha
ve-shari, or not and it's permitted? תא שמע, ta shma, come and
hear, ולא בקמיע בזמן שאינו מן המומחה. ve-lo ve-kmeia bizman she-eino min
ha-mumche. So don't wear it when it's not from an expert. הא
מן המומחה, ha min ha-mumche, נפיק, nofeik, if it is an expert,
you can wear it. I think that's explicit in another משנה Mishna
anyway. ואי אמרת קמיע יש בהם משום קדושה, ve-im amart kmeia yesh
bahem mishum kedusha, if they have קדושה kedusha and you have to
take them off before going into a bathroom, זימנין דמיצטריך לבית הכיסא,
zimnin de-mitztareich le-veit ha-kisei, sometimes you'll be, need to go to the
bathroom outdoors, ואתי לאתויי ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים, ve-ati le-asuyei arba amot
bi-reshut ha-rabim, and you'll take it off and come to carry it.
So it can't be we would ever demand you take it off,
because then we would not allow you to wear it on שבת.
Shabbat. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הכא במאי עסקינן בקמיע של
עיקרין. hacha be-mai askinan be-kmeia shel ikarin. No, when we say you're
allowed to wear it, that's only one that's of the herbs, not
one that has an actual script in it. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, and therefore it's not a problem about, because then
you won't take it off when you go to the bathroom. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והתניא, ve-hatanya, we a ברייתא Baraita
says, אחד קמיע של כתב ואחד קמיע של עיקרין. echad kmeia shel
ktav ve-echad kmeia shel ikarin. We just quoted this before. Whether it's
one with a, like a parchment in it, some writing in it,
or whether it's one of herbs, you're allowed to wear it if
it's been proven. So and therefore you see you won't take it
off even if you're going into a bathroom. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אלא הכא במאי עסקינן בחולה שיש בו סכנה. ela hacha be-mai
askinan be-choleh she-yesh bo sakana. We're talking about somebody that has a
סכנה. sakana. So even if we normally demand you take a קמיע
kmeia off before going into the bathroom, if this is a person
that his life is at risk, so we would not demand that
he take the קמיע kmeia off. We'd let him wear it in
the bathroom because it still have to, it has to protect him
at all times. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והתניא, ve-hatanya,
the ברייתא Baraita says, אחד חולה שיש בו סכנה ואחד חולה שאין
בו סכנה, echad choleh she-yesh bo sakana ve-echad choleh she-ein bo sakana,
that if it's a proven קמיע, kmeia, you can wear it if,
if you're a sick person, even if your life is not in
danger. So how are we letting a sick person whose life is
not in danger wear a קמיע kmeia with God's name on it?
Why are we not afraid that they will come to,
that they'll take it off before going into the bathroom? So the
fact that we're not afraid shows that we're not, you don't have
to take it off before going into the bathroom. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אלא כיון דמסי, ela keivan de-masi, since it heals, אף
על פי דנקיט ליה בידיה נמי שפיר דמי. af al pi de-nakit
lei be-yadei nami shapir dami. So this is a wild answer, which
is, something that is healing you, you can actually carry in your
hand, and that's not considered carrying on שבת, Shabbat, which is, which
is wild. Until now we spoke about wearing it, and even there
we said wearing it, but it's not clothing, but you need it,
so it's not a burden. Here it says maybe even holding onto
it in your hand and carrying in your hand is seen as
maybe part of your body and it's not carrying. So the גמרא,
Gemara, one minute, the גמרא Gemara rejects this. והתניא, ve-hatanya, but we
taught in the ברייתא, Baraita, רבי אושעיה אומר, Rabbi Oshaya omer, ובלבד
שלא יאחזנו בידו ויעבירנו ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים. u-vilvad she-lo yochozenu be-yado
ve-ya'avirenu arba amot bi-reshut ha-rabim. No, I'm sorry, you cannot have it
in your hand. Meaning that would be an answer: you'd have to
take it off, but we're not concerned that you'll carry it because
there's no such thing as carrying because it's always considered to be
part of your body. But that's not true. Actually, if you're not
wearing it, it is considered carrying. So we're back to our problem.
Why do we let you wear this? Why aren't we afraid you'll
take it off and going into the bathroom? We tried to give
a radical answer that even if you carried it, it would not
be a problem, but we rejected that. So and so if we're
not concerned, it must prove that you're allowed to go into a
bathroom with this on. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא הכא במאי
עסקינן, ela hacha be-mai askinan, here I'll explain to you why it's
permitted here specifically, because obviously the גמרא's Gemara is resisting this. If
it's got God's name in it, so who, you know, you don't
want it in a bathroom. So here's a special case. What's the
case? במחופה עור. bi-mechupa or. It's covered with leather. And somehow in
a leather pouch that is considered to be like completely, completely put
away, completely non-exposed, and that's okay, which is fine. Normally the גמרא
Gemara demands it be in like a double wrap in order like
your airline food but no actually the גמרא Gemara does demand that
by תפילין Tefillin in order for you to take it into like
a bathroom, but here somehow it said covered with leather, that suffices.
You had a question, Ari?
No, about carrying in an יש בו סכנה.
yesh bo sakana. יש בו סכנה.
yesh
bo sakana. Oh, what's the problem?
No, that's true, but even אין בו ein bo because we had
just proven אין בו סכנה, ein bo sakana, right? The גמרא Gemara
said, the ברייתא Baraita just said even אין בו סכנה ein bo
sakana it was still willing to say that carrying it was not
an issue. But it rejected that. Clearly carrying is an issue. It's
a big issue by the way. My grandmother
עליו השלום alav hashalom had to have her nitroglycerin pills on her
at all times, you know, and so what do you do if
there's no עירוב? Eruv? You know, so do you make a necklace
out I mean, you know, there's something that you needed available to
you, but it's not actively healing, you know, and there
how does that compare to these issues where these things are seen
as actively healing? But there also is a case about carrying in
the hand, and carrying in the hand even for these are not
good. Well, let's just finish this. The גמרא Gemara says like this,
so the גמרא Gemara says it's covered with leather. הרי תפילין דמחופה
עור. harei tefillin de-mechupa or. One minute, תפילין Tefillin is leather boxes
covering the scrolls inside. ותניא הנכנס לבית הכסא, ve-tanya ha-nichnas le-veit ha-kisei,
if you're going into a bathroom, חולץ תפילין בריחוק ארבע אמות. choletz
tefillin be-richok arba amot. You have to take your תפילין Tefillin off
ארבע אמות arba amot outside of the bathroom. ונכנס, ve-nichnas, so you
go in. So you see covered with leather is not good. And
it says no, התם משום שין. hatam mishum shin. There the boxes
themselves have the קדושה kedusha of God's name because of the שין
shin that's inscribed on the
תפילין של ראש. tefillin shel rosh. דאמר אביי שין של תפילין הלכה
למשה מסיני, de-amar abaye shin shel tefillin halakha le-moshe mi-sinai, that the
שין shin is a הלכה למשה מסיני halakha le-moshe mi-sinai and that
gives the קדושה kedusha to the actual box itself. ואמר אביי דלת
של תפילין, ve-amar abaye dalet shel tefillin, the דלת dalet that's in
the knot in the back of your head, הלכה למשה מסיני. halakha
le-moshe mi-sinai. ואמר אביי יוד של תפילין הלכה למשה מסיני. ve-amar abaye
yud shel tefillin halakha le-moshe mi-sinai. So there the תפילין tefillin is
different. רש"י Rashi says the שין דלת יוד shin dalet yud are
all part of God's name. תוספות Tosafot says that that's actually just
גירסא girsa is a wrong גירסא. girsa. תוספות Tosafot says only the
שין shin has קדושת השם. kedushat hashem. The other things which are
not actually written, you know, they're not but they're just made by
knots are not really considered to be letters and the real thing
that has קדושת השם kedushat hashem is just the שין shin which
represents God's name.
The יד yad has the יד yad doesn't have a שין.
shin. So there's actually a question about taking off the יד. yad.
So we'll see about that at a later time. So anyway the
answer is that תפילין, Tefillin, it's not good that's covered by leather
because it itself has קדושה, kedusha, but by the קמיע kame'a we've
come to the conclusion even with God's name it's okay if it's
covered with leather. Let's just finish to the משנה. Mishnah. The last
thing totally unrelated now to the קמיעות kame'as is you cannot wear
various types of armor, again it's only a rabbinic concern. So לא
בשריון ולא בקסדא ולא במגפיים. lo be-shiryon ve-lo be-kasta ve-lo be-magafayim. So
what is this? שריון זרדא, shiryon zrada, which is basically like armor,
chain metal or armor. קסדא אמר רב סנוארתא kasta amar rav snuarta
which is a helmet, okay. And מגפיים אמר רב פזמקי magafayim amar
rav pazmakei which are leg armor. Okay, and there're beautiful pictures there
in Steinsaltz. So we will continue with all of this tomorrow.